我想。
噉就誒。
我哋有足夠嘅人數。
下一個項目咧，就係。
預期參加委員會嘅申請。
啊！我宣佈今日嘅會議開始。
阿馬請請大家留低，我哋有足夠人數處理下一個項目。
噉啊，上次開會之後咧，啊就發出咗啊發出嘅資料文件咧，啊係冇嘅。
凡係響委員。
當作逾期參加委員會嘅申請。
咁根據內務守則第二十三括弧C。
誒嘅編號就係立法會C.B.括弧一。
誒英士明加入委員會嘅期限之後咧，就提出關於誒士明加入有關委員會嘅問題，係需。
九九一stroke十八hyphen十九括弧零一號嘅文件，咁亦都係響誒今年嘅五月二號咧，就發送咗畀大家嘅。
噉啊，譚文浩議員嘅申請咧，係需根據內務守則第二十三條嘅規定處理嘅。按照內務守則第二十三括弧A條咧。
我收到阿譚文浩議員嘅一份文件咧，佢就響二零一九年四月三十號咧就啊表示啊希望加入呢個聯合小組委員會。咁譚議員嘅函件咧。
係，或者啊。
依封信係冇講理由嘅，或者我請阿阿譚議員講講好嗎？
大家有冇其他意見？嗱，如果冇其他意見咧，我就啊。
噉我而家咧就誒請問委員誒同唔同意接受誒譚議員嘅預期申請？
係啊，馬議員，想問下啊啊啊，譚文浩議員有冇畀咩理由？點解之前唔入，而家要入嘅？佢封信又冇寫喎。
所以喺誒我哋黨裏邊嘅分工咧，就少少變咗。我係誒就我給發翻佢喺呢一方面嘅誒嘅會議，咁所以點解我喺呢度加入啦嚇？嗯。
誒條咧，如果逾期參參加嘅委員會嘅申請係基於響英士明加入委員會嘅期間身體不適或者不在香港以外嘅理由，啊，該項申請啦就應否獲得接納咧，就係由委員會大家決定嘅。
請委員。
啊嘅代表參加今日嘅會議。
咁亦都歡迎啊啊譚議員加入。
噉我都誒唔逐個介紹啦，因為大家都係。
歡迎誒政府嘅代表同埋西九。
誒，依個議題咧就係M加發展嘅最新進展。
誒委員會嘅委員咧就誒批准有關嘅申請，大家同意啊嘛，OK。
跟住落嚟咧，就首先或者我哋請有關誒政府官員同埋西九管理局嘅代表咧，就進入會議室。
誒多謝主席。誒，其實最主要咧都係因為誒本身即係高文房嘅分工咧，都係阿陳素莊議員係負責西九文化區嘅。咁其實大家可能喺新聞報章都可能知道，其實佢身體都仍然係不適，相信佢都會有一段時間都未必係可以出席到立法會嘅會議，包括呢個西九小組。咁所，
please。
The whole M+ project.
政府首先介紹。
老朋友嚟咗好多次啦。
咁或者我請誒。
And then the final three rows are the facade.
So you can see here a picture. This is looking from.
誒，今日有關嘅項目好嘛？依個就係M。
Good afternoon, members. So, just like to take you through a few short slides to show you the construction progress of where we are with our M Plus Museum.
All of the podium is finished, and you know the facade of the main tower. You can just actually see in the very front of the picture that that hole is is for the the project adjacent, which is the the Lyric Theatre.
What we call the ABWF and the MEP. So you can see there on the right-hand column the progress that we're currently tracking on the project, and overall it's around sixty odd percent.
Thank you, Chair. Mr. Chairman, we've put together a short presentation in two parts. The first part deals with the current state of the construction project. Second part deals with the current state of the museum establishment. So I'll ask Jeremy to do the first part and Suhanya to do the second part. Thank you.
M plus發展嘅最新進展。好，誒多謝主席。或者喺M家最新發展咧，因為主要呢個係一個文化藝術嘅項目啦。咁而西九喺呢方面咧係有一個誒自主權嘅，或者我直接請阿白志高先生介紹關於M家嘅最新發展嚇。
So another view here to show the podium. This is a view, obviously, from
A fitout period internally, so we're hoping to get everything externally completed this year.
And we also have a few skylights that are being put in, and all that should be completed in the next few months.
That Sahani and a team can show artwork on etc, and obviously it will be used at night time, and you'll be able to see it from across the harbour etc.
Have a lot of natural light which is coming in, and in the next month or so, we will just be putting the glazing into that large space. You can see at the top.
Just a nice visual there. That's looking west. We have some very beautiful sunsets out of the out of the building. This is from one of the main galleries in the in the museum.
Facade installation is going up along the side of the buildings. You can see there, it's about a third, thirty-two percent, about a third of the way up, and also fitout works is is going on inside too.
Around the end of this month, and a lot of the mechanical, electrical and plumbing installation inside that tower is ongoing, as well as much of the architectural builder's works and finishes, which is also going on in the tower.
just a view along the facade, a little bit difficult to see, but Zichu is actually right down the far side, in the background, in the middle of the picture. So you can see that this is the first part of what will be our promenade, which will go all the way down the.
So we can see here, just a short table. On the left-hand column, is really the area of work. So we have the tower, the podium, basement, conservation storage facility, and the RDE. So that they are the core parts of the.
North to south, you can see there in the foreground, that is the retail dining and entertainment building, the 16-storey building that will have retail in and also our offices above, and obviously in the background the main M+ museum, and you can see.
So this is a view from the south, looking north, and again the main feature there is the the sixteen storey tower, and you can see that the facade panels are more or less complete. There, the lift installations are in progress and should be finished.
The south looking north, and you can see from the notes on that slide that we're doing a lot of the waterproofing to the podium deck and on also the early aspects of the hard landscaping. Because all of that podium deck will be landscaped.
So just moving on, this structure here is the conservation and storage, or the CSF building. This is where a lot of the artwork will be stored and looked after and transported from this building into the main museum. So the workshops at the top of the building there.
This building is the what we call the RDE building, and you can see there. As of today, we're up to the fifteen th floor as regards the structure. So we're almost at the top of the building. The roof has just got to go on now, and basically in parallel, the
香港。
博物館。
和 podium area。
Yeah，thank you.
Only the avenue. Sorry, I'm being reminded the avenue.
That's about a nine-storey building. This one, eight nine-storey.
Okay, so I'll hand over to Sir Hania just to go through some of the software side of the.
as well, so the quality is is really you know what we've been looking for on the project, and very happy to date.
Thank you. Good, very nice to be here to talk about the content of this extraordinary institution.
We're also doing some of what we call the art walls inside the galleries. So these are the walls you can see there. They sit off.
The concrete walls and you can actually get around the back of them, and this will be for Sahania and her team to actually install all the future artwork. So we're actually installing those walls now as well in the galleries.
87 object collections that includes the M+ collection and 35,000 collection archives, which are primarily from our architectural holdings and some design. So you can see a very substantial group of Hong Kong makers are part of those collections.
Here's a nice image from our park. This is from the west, because as you may know from our master plan, the park nicely leads in to the museum building from the west. You walk from the park up a sort of lawned area, a winding pathway, and
You enter into the museum, and that nicely takes you up to the podium decks and the galleries that are in the museum. So you can see here we've already started some of the landscaping work to the west side. There's some grass and lamp posts etc. are all going in, so that the project really is moving into.
And final few slides. This is obviously a close up of the facade on the south side, and this facade, as you may know, has integrated into it an LED screen that's sort of embedded, and this this will be a screen.
And just a few slides that you know, this is inside the tower, so you can see there's a lot of fit out going on inside, and obviously all of the major mechanical, electrical and plumbing, which is being which is quite extensive, which is being fitted out in the tower.
And of course, finally, just a few of the finishes that we've built benchmarks and mock-ups for, and these are all ready to be installed in the final building. And you can see here, you know, some toilets that we've also constructed as benchmarks.
係。
and。
學生 in attendance.
This is clearly a destination when they decide to come and visit us.
with an attendance of over 76,000 students reached.
To develop our M Plus International Programme, we began with the Hidden Pulse, a collaboration with the Sydney Opera House that has just taken place.
own M Plus internship internship programme at the museum, where we really want to think about the sustainability of this museum into the future.
Beyond, this scheme initiated in 2017 and now starting to really see wonderful works coming in. 23% of the works that we've acquired are from Hong Kong.
Charlotte say， this time， marvellous new work that she made， working very closely with Christina Lee as our guest curator。just over those first two weeks of opening， we had over 12,000 people visiting our pavilion。
And this slide gives you a quick summary of where we are up to with the collection. It's a global museum, a museum that doesn't exist in Hong Kong yet, and so something that we are contributing very substantially to in terms of the cultural capital of Hong Kong. The collection now sits at 6,380.
我 wanted to show you this slide because it also gives you a quick summary of the fact that this collection is recognised internationally for its excellence, and we have a very active loans programme where we are lending these works while we are waiting for the museum to open, and it's our way of championing the work that we are doing here in.
In terms of the building of the collections, we have also now started to establish some of our development arms of what we're doing, including a council for new art, which is a patronage scheme to support the acquisitions of works by young artists from the Greater China region that includes Hong Kong, mainland China, Taiwan and.
Of course, we are always looking at our engagement and how we work with Hong Kong audiences. Our M Plus Rover continues. This time, the emerging artist that we worked with is Na Kachun, wonderful artist, and we reached seventy four schools across Hong Kong.
This time for during the Art Basel Hong Kong, we had a pavilion within the convention centre, and we worked with four makers from Hong Kong to talk about what does it mean to be a creative practitioner working with an institution like M+.
At the same time, we had our Naguchi for Jan Vou counterpoint exhibition at our M+ pavilion. Over twenty zero people attended that. And during the Hong Kong Art Basel week, two and a just just under two and a half zero visitors came to see us at that point. It's wonderful because.
Our outreach is essential, and I just wanted to start to introduce you to the fact that we're reaching out to special needs schools as well, and a central part of our engagement with community. And this time, twelve participating schools with two hundred and fifty-seven.
係。
誒。
Thank you.
索償嗰部分就向AIG嚟到誒收翻呢一個嘅誒。
Thank you。噉啊，而家係議員發問嘅時間，每位四分鐘。譚文浩議員。
你唔可以加啲數字上，因為四百萬係單純一個點喺時間嘅評估。
管理人嘅決定，相信呢個所謂嘅決定就係話誒個決定意思係即係話終止咁簡單啦，定係呢個決定係包含咗一個嘅錢喺度嘅，即係話而家誒誒終止咗同新窗合約，令到誒新窗變咗，導致到成單工程。
We have also again for the fourth time partnered with Hong Kong Arts Development Council to present Hong Kong's Venice Pavilion as part of the collateral events there. Venice Biennale is the largest international platform for contemporary art, and so it is a real honour to be able to have brought.
As part of delivering that project, we also work with young technical and curatorial interns. Twelve of them this time, helping us to stage and facilitate that event in Venice. Very important training for us, and that pairs up with our.
The collaboration for that we have undertaken with international museums is now taking on a different arm, if you like. We've had ten M Plus mobile exhibitions in Hong Kong and nine now in the M Plus Pavilion. In the lead up to the opening of the museum, we're now starting.
Of course, we have our strategic corporate framework with the Power Station of Art in Shanghai. This is a long-term collaboration where we will look to tour selected exhibitions, curate large-scale exhibitions together, and look at our collections and how we can share collections and archives.
多謝主席。誒，我即係一個新委員啦，可能我有啲問題咧，可能係比較誒對於你嚟講簡單少少，不過我自己可能要搞清楚有啲事件先。咁咧，第一咧，我就想問咧，關於呢一個嘅誒新窗嗰件事嘅。咁誒文件其實你第十。
六段交代咗啦。本來個合約咧就係五十九億四千幾萬嘅，咁而家好明顯啦。噉啊，應該都會係會超過呢個錢啦。咁最後而家究竟幾多錢，你就話未夠未可以透露。只不過文件第十七段咧，你就話咧，其實誒呢一個嘅三步曲啦，第一步咧就係合約。
係會用多咗幾多錢？係咪就係呢一部曲嘅嘢？如果係嘅話，咁呢個決定係咪其實已經可以講到畀大家聽？係啊，嗰個錢係幾多咧？亦係咪即係等於喺第十八段所講嘅，就係而家可以披露中子合誒新窗以嚟所花嘅誒誒成本係超過。
嘅。
Let me stress the word offset, additional cost.
simple statements who keep give members the most up-to-date position.
Contract will only be possible once we have got to the stage called.
有冇嗰個數字啊？About six hundred, about six hundred, yeah, about six hundred million. Okay, thank you.
provided the bond as they should because it's an on-demand bond. Hence, we're in the court. That money will of course help to offset.
佢有三個步驟㗎嘛？誒，合約管理人嘅決定、調解同埋進仲裁嚇。咁而家咧就叫做。
項目實際完工後一年保養期屆滿之後開始，噉佢括住就係話，二零二一年嘅第二季先至可以確定嘅。
on top of that, there is also retention money as there would be under any normal contract in Hong Kong, and we have some retention money which will also help to offset some of the costs. But let me stress the final resolution of this.
The bond is an entirely separate issue. It's called an on-demand bond. It can be claimed under certain conditions set out in the contract. We have called for that bond. Unfortunately, the bonds man in this case AIG have not yet.
essentially practical completion, which is at the end of the project, because that's when you know what the final cost will be. So what we're trying to do is to give members as much information as we can as of the dates that are are presented here.
所以，我怕唔係單單係X減Y等於Z，唔係噉樣。Can you also tell last questions about the retention, the retention money? How much is that there? It's five percent of the original contract price, which is equal to.
四億咧，即係簡單而言咧，成條成條問題就係話，而家因為新窗唔能夠繼續嚟到興建，而導致到暫時睇到嘅損失係四億。咁呢個係最核心嘅問題。而跳落下一個問題咧，就係關於第十九段嘅噉，就係話嗰個嘅。
即係二點九七億嘅港元，噉係咪即係呢一部分係我嚟cover翻？誒文件部分嘅第十八段嗰四億幾咧，係咪個度？我當佢三億到啦，係咪即係代表？如果從一條簡單嘅數學題，其實係咪講緊就係話，因為新窗嘅原因，所以
係四億，不過咧，你應該就可以。如果攞得翻曬A.I.G.賠嗰個錢咧，就大約三億，所以最後咧就其實就新槍因為新槍而真係蝕嘅而有claim唔到保險嘅，其實係講緊一億係咪噉樣嘅意思咧？咁如果總之比較簡單啲。
方法可以解釋到畀我聽，究竟個中嘅關係嘅話，咁誒誒，希望有關當局可以解釋一下呢一幾條嘅聯繫係乜嘢唔該主席。啊，帕茲高生。Mr. Chairman, I think let me start with the last question first, because it's it's it's fundamental to the answer. No, is the simple answer to your question.
of the additional cost arising from the termination, the termination has taken place. The dispute is over that termination, and that obviously is subject to the mechanism set out in the contract, which is through mediation. If not, then we take it to arbitration. That's a separate issue. In terms of the figures that are presented here, it's
In respect of the additional cost, now the additional cost and who pays for that is one of the issues that will have to be resolved through this mechanism. And there will be claims from us against the contractor, depending on what the final cost is. Those claims will be equal to that final cost.
那係最best case。
第二個 issue 是，how much we can claim back.
And we will certainly be pursuing both of those.
the either party to declare a dispute.
所以那係一 issue，那那 fact會被 known 當 the building is complete， for obvious reasons。
預算過嗰個損失會係幾多咧？會唔會影響你整體嗰個財務安排咧？咁？
有冇預計預算講？Mr. Chairman，If I'm being really optimistic，we get everything back and we don't have to pay anything。
對於整個西九項目文化局嗰個流動資金會唔會有一個一個影響？
As I say, the final resolution in terms of the the actual price will depend on various factors. The first thing is how much is it going to cost us extra to complete the building.
主席，即係佢佢講緊下一次彙報，其實都係嘅下屆立法會嘅事。我就問，如果真係最壞嘅情況，會唔會影響到佢哋嘅成個成個資金嚇？
There are there is another issue which is even more complicated called legacy claims, which are the outstanding claims that we would make against the contractor for the work that they should have done, and that I don't particularly want to get into that now.
realistically, if we win everything we win everything. If we lose everything we lose everything. That's the worst case. the the issue here really is a situation as I described in in my answer to the earlier question, that we have to follow the steps provided for in the contract. The contract provides for
Let me just add one more thing. You said how do you monitor? Well, the whole point is that we will report regularly, as we said in paragraph 18, we will report the turn out cost of this project to members in due course, and we will keep this up to date as soon as we as we proceed.
誒，跟住係陳志全議員係誒，唔該主席。其實舊年十一月咧，我已經向西九管理局查詢，就係話新窗營造拖欠佢分判商費用嘅總額係乜嘢啦。噉我哋今次睇到文件十七段就話，到今年六月咧，合約爭議解決程序咧就只係做第一步噉。
爭議程序嘅第一步已經得到履行，即係講緊係決定咗嗰個合約管理人啫。咁嗱，十八段佢就話管理局仍可披露自中止聘用新槍營造以嚟所花費嘅成本咧，就係誒超過四億，但係項目最終成本咧就需在
噉我哋個本屆立法會咧，就去到下年嘅七月啦。咁二零一二一年嘅第二季咧，就唔知邊個喺度，到時有冇呢個小組委員會都係到時嘅事啦。即係話我哋而家根本喺呢呢一呢個點上咧，就跟進唔到，監察唔到。
咁其實有冇一個最最好同最壞嘅一個預算，可以話畀公眾知道，或者話話畀議會知道咧？咁仲如果嗱，第二嘅叫仲裁誒調解啦。咁如果仲調解就即係講數啊。如果仲裁啦，仲裁當你如果你輸輸曬啦噉樣咁管理局有冇？
sorry。
啊！
有冇其他問題？
會好啲咧，陳主席。
reclaim that money which has cost beyond the original budget.
Mr. Stow will answer that. Sure, thank you.
噉啊，多謝各位參加今次嘅會議，噉。
costs that we know will be coming towards us, whether we get this money back or not. So yes, that that's all been provided for.或者我咁問一問啦，如果收翻曬就冇問題啦，但係如果一毫子都收唔到嘅，咁會唔會誒有一個比較大啲嘅影響咧？
The dispute declaration has to be assessed in a sense in the first stage by the independent contract administrator. That has been done. So we're now into the second stage, which is mediation, and we'll be responding to the request for mediation shortly. So I don't particularly want to get into that detail.
from the original contractor, and that's something that we'll have to work through this process looking at our losses. The third factor is obviously to secure the bond, which is an on-demand bond, which will help us to offset some of the cost. There is the retention money, which again I've explained.
Mr. Chairman, obviously we have to look at our cash flow situation, but we have taken provision in the budget and we did announce the budget to members. I think at the previous meeting, so that information is already available to members if you want to look it up. Yes, we monitor the situation very closely, but we have to make provision for.
Yeah, I mean, Mr. Chairman, we have to budget as if we can't recover anything. Okay. Otherwise, we couldn't we couldn't complete the project. In order to complete the project, we must budget to complete the cost. Okay. But that's only a budget for this stage. We we fully anticipate seeking to to.
啊！易志明議員。
主席啊，我想請問。
from buildings department and fire services department.
噉啊，中間個中場休息啊，十五分鐘。
誒，如果我問嘅問題同M加無關嘅？
嗱，我就最近有機會咧，就去戲曲中心就睇咗個話劇。
出年三月嗰個日子係可以完成嘅，好多謝。
香港嘅工人好好，所以唔好欠佢哋薪啊！啊，你好信心嗰個新嘅。
但係同呢個場地嘅硬件有關，我問唔問得啊？你你問你問咗先啦，好嘛？
是，你可以get an amazing response from our workers. When they put their mind to it, they can really deliver against timetable. And I, I have to say, we're very confident that the workers in Hong Kong will deliver this project to the new timetable.
that we have to go through the statutory inspection process at the end of this year, the beginning of next year, which is always complicated, and you know we wait to see how that goes with with our government colleagues.
唔似係其他裝修工程，我呢個係都係幾幾骨幹幾重要嘅工程，都只不過係去到四十二個percent。噉我有啲擔心係係咪真係都講得及咧？嗱，其實已經遲咗㗎啦，下年三月。我有啲擔心係咪最後下年三月都講唔到，即係講唔切，咁點算咧？噉樣。
你你哋舉手得太遲啊！唔緊要，我畀我畀你哋。啊，康俊宇議員，跟住就係啊啊葉志明議員。係多謝主席，亦都多謝咁多位啊。因為咧，其實我就比較關注咧，即係呢一個即係M加工程嘅進度咧，係令我幾擔心。因為當中咧七個嘅工程項目咧。
裏邊啦，得兩個係已完成。咁曾經有講過啦，因為之前有新窗嘅事件啦，喺新窗嘅事件之後咧，就到金門咧去接接受咗呢個工程，就話儘量趕工。咁曾經指咧就二零一九年年底咧就去搞掂啦。咁咁今日咧就誒二零一九年五月三十一號，其實距離個完工日期咧都越嚟越。
問可能而家都仲有約摸半年嘅時間，當中七個項目得兩個已完成啦，我係非常之擔心。我想睇睇其實係咪仍然係樂觀，定還是你哋都會開始會修整嗰個嘅即係完工日期嘅預算，會唔會喺呢度已經可以向公眾去即係畀定啲預？
Yes, there's about five, five or six elements to the project in total, and some of the more minor ones have been completed. But when we terminated the employment of Sinchong last year, the first task when we sat down with the new management contractor, Gammon.
was to review the outstanding work and agree a programme, and I'm pleased to say we have agreed a programme, and that is to achieve the occupations permit by March, end of March next year. Now that is a delay compared to the original contract. I mean, since
With their work were consistently in delay, so we do have a new project timeline, and it is is to achieve next year. The risk of the work that's that's left to do, I mean, it's been quite a complicated project building over the airport railway.
Lot of the civils and structural works, but the nature of the works that's left is quite low risk. It's sort of fit-out works internally, so all the you know heavy civils and structural works is completed. So we do have a reasonable level of confidence in achieving the programme that's left. But I would emphasise.
啊！就住呢一個嘅即係工程咧，其實已經係即係一再延期嘅，因為咧其實最初咧，如果冇新窗事件咧，係更更早嘅情況下，當然係順利地完成咗啦。而家本身係二零一九年年底，而家再到咧就二零二零年三月。誒，聽落去就係即係話哦，呢個就係我哋畀咗個。
責任畀外盤商即金門係應承我哋，但係我哋睇誒個資料咧，都令我即係我特別擔心，好有可能係一個基建工程嗰個區域供冷系統啦、地庫啦同埋橫向嘅基座平台啦，已完成四十二個percent嘅安裝工程，即係我感覺係即係呢類呢個。
Mr. Chairman, in fact, as we as we presented in the slideshow earlier, the work is is actually progressing very well in terms of all of the the difficult bits. What's left is relatively straightforward, as my colleague has explained. And the wonderful thing about Hong Kong.
分別好多。
誒排長龍。
都有五千幾行嘅。
噉啊，但係。
我都有個問題想問，係。
咁咧，我就見到個女士洗手間咧，就虛冚啦。
全港你唔會一齊去㗎嘛，但係當你去睇一啲嘅表演，誒嗱。
啊！葉議員響呢個戲曲中心睇到嗰啲問題啦，我哋響M加嗰度唔會發生。
In the in the Seisure Centre, we're now going to three to one in the Lyric Theatre because we've learnt from that experience. But honestly, I could put in four to one or five to one, and we'd probably still have the same problem.
我我我針對個劇場。Mr. Chairman, in in fact, I understand. I can give you the figures separately, but I will do. Can I just make a general statement? Honestly, when you have a short intermission, it doesn't matter if you have a hundred toilet seats. Probably never going to be enough.
咁咧就有問題嘅嗱。咁其實咧，香港表演場地咧不嬲都有呢個問題嘅。咁但係呢個新起㗎嘛。噉我就第一想問咧，嗰個戲曲中心裏邊個劇場究竟有幾多座位？日流喺嗰個Lyrics誒Fiesta有幾多座位？大劇院有幾多座位？你哋嗰個規劃有冇諗？
清楚，因為嗰啲未起啊嘛，咁希望你真係有足夠嘅position啊！即係我嗰日見到就真係非常虛恆，或或者我同你執一執個問題啦。M加裏邊啊，會唔會有好似戲曲中心裏邊呢個廁所嗰方面嘅問題咧？
The issue for us is making sure that we have the capacity to get people through within that fifteen minute time frame. And at the moment, we're just about doing it. Having said that, we're looking at the Lyric Theatre to increase the ratio of toilets. We already have a I think it's a two to one ratio, female to male, in.
係，係，係。
係。
Thank you.
誒。
As you know, we are a
just the office one, not the private one.
先生，議員，我 ask Sir Henry to answer that one.
O.K.咁今個環節咧就到此為止，咁亦都多謝。
誒政府同埋細狗有關嘅代表咧，參加依次嘅會議。咁下一節咧就係。
and can see the 5,000 objects that we have recently put up as part of our collections beta.
Thank you. If I can just add, I take the point about the website as a whole, and in fact, we're now doing a revamp of the website, and I hope to get that online soon.
因為我們做每樣嘢用兩種語言，我們有要檢查和確保每一個資訊我們放上網是準確，和反映它需要的，所以。
Yeah, well actually I'm I'm glad you know my friends are telling me they are very interested and they have some difficulties in searching for those material. Yes, so I can tell them. It'll it'll get better progressively. Should I give them your phone number? Please do.
誒啊，Mr. Prescott，即係響依一方面，可唔可以介紹一下啊？或者係響宣傳嗰方面咧，係可以做得多啲咁多，因為好多人都想去睇嘅，但係而家咧，佢哋覺得有有少少困難嘅。
音樂會啊，仲閉，因為冇中間，你入唔到去，你就好難再翻埋去嘅。噉你睇話劇都仲有機會去轉場景個刻咧，仲可以攝埋去。咁但係咧就即係嗰次見到嘅現象咧，我就真係希望你哋喺未來起緊嗰啲硬件嗰度咧係留心下呢個問題啦。好嘛，依依個意見嚟嘅，即係希望誒。
我我想問一問，就係有關M家博物館，其實咧而家已經有三萬幾項嗰啲資料，咁咧就啊，我都知道，亦都喺網上邊咧開始將一啲啊依啲藏品咧啊依啲資料列出嚟嘅，咁暫時咧就我睇。
我識好多朋友咧，佢就話：啊，喂，佢點樣去睇啊？啊，點樣？啊啊，可可以分享啊？咁同埋點樣去搜響即係搜索嗰啲列出嚟嗰啲啊不同行品嗰度咧，就佢哋覺得唔係好方便㗎。噉我想問一問。
We are developing our collections online website with the intention of having everything online by the time we open. We have over five thousand objects now available online, and we're slowly beginning the project of adding to that. That includes our archival collections.
Under construction institution that includes our collection managers and all of those stuff coming online as we get ready. So by the end of by the time we open, the whole collection will be available, and we are phasing those collections coming online. I'm very happy to hear that you have friends who are already looking.
咁咧就或者首先請政府講講先好嘛。
而被批地文件嘅最新進展。
西九文化區A發展組合同埋。
文件嘅一啲誒重點嘅誒項目嚇，多謝。
理解的的的context，ACE是三元素，它。
The site, it's important to see it in the context because it is very central. I'm not sure if this this thing's working. Doesn't matter. It's very central to this whole western end of the district.
誒多謝主席。誒其實根據喺二零一七年一月十八號公佈嘅維西九推行嘅加強財務安排咧，政府係將以漲徵式嘅地價批出西九文化區入邊嘅酒店、辦公室、住宅部分，包括係誒藝術。
商業同埋展覽嘅發展組合，即係ensure咧，就係A.C.E嘅組合部分啦。咁同埋容許管理局咧，同發展商簽訂一啲嘅合作協議，同埋攤分收入嘅安排咧，係為咗係令到管理局咧有一個穩定嘅經常性嘅收入來源嘅。咁其實我哋喺二零一八年六月十一號咧。
喺個聯合小組咧，以簡介個A C嘅項目發展。咁今日咧，我哋係想誒誒更新呢個誒彙報嘅。咁管理局咧就係剛發出邀請，係誒請一啲係有興趣與西九文化區合作嘅私營機構，喺今年八月咧就係就A C項目遞交發展意向。
書咁管理局就會根據發展意向書審議嘅結果咧，就預計喺第四季係發出一個標書，明年第三季批出標書，以期喺二零二五年能夠完成A C嘅發展項目嘅。咁亦都為咗推進呢個項目同埋係實踐嗰陣時嘅加強財務安排咧，正。
府喺批地個方面嘅誒法律嘅工作咧，要有所跟進同埋配合嘅。咁所以政府咧，亦都係誒而家準備緊呢個批地文件，係會將土地嘅業權係畀管理局，誒等佢可以發展同埋營運西九文化區嘅。咁批地嘅文件咧，係會確保同埋有助管理局。
二零二五。
the。
and all these three elements will be part of the project.
facilities in Hong Kong, carried out by AMR, that determined that the demand
5,000平方公尺總，是，內一個55平方公尺的範圍，所以係一個相當大的發展區。
We expect this to be of interest to a consortium type approach of different expertise bringing in their relevant skill set.
the the target as I said is to release this to tap into the expertise and the capability of the private sector.
We'll be opening the Palace Museum in middle of 2022. We'll then open the Lyric Theatre Complex in 2023-24, and the intention is the next one to come online would be ACE in around 2025.
shortfall in Hong Kong is expected to be quite substantial over the next ten years for exhibition and this sort of space. So we know that there is demand and we believe that we will be tapping into that market.
is the tenderer the combination that brings with it their financial capability etc. We will then shortlist a number, possibly four, possibly five. We're still working on that. Depends on the quality of the expression of interest for
係依據以前我哋已經向個小組匯報過嘅政策目的啦，係推展西九嘅藝術項目嘅，同埋係一啲誒發展一啲商業嘅元素，而支持西九去經營呢啲藝術嘅文化藝術嘅項目嘅。咁當中咧，亦都係包括將西九土地發展咧為一個。
誒由中向由橫向嘅文化藝術區同埋落實個加強財務安排嘅噉，我首先咧就會請行政總裁柏志高先生解釋呢個A C E發展組合嘅內容噉，然後咧亦都請誒民政事務局入邊嘅工程策劃總監應芬芳女士咧誒簡單介紹批定。
Mr. Chairman, if I can take members through this, in fact this morning we held a press conference to announce the release of the expression of interest exercise, and the various documentations will be available from the twelve th of June. So let me just briefly take you through what we're planning with this ACE.
That's the location, as members can see from the slide here. It's the northern, northwestern portion of the site, plus the area over what we call the U-shaped road. That comprises the ACE as a as a combination. But I think it's quite important that we.
From our side, it covers art, it covers commerce, it covers exhibitions. It's to be built under a build-operate-transfer arrangement in accordance with the EFA provisions. And the objective is very simple: we want to capture the market capability and opportunities in design and construction of management.
within the next few years, as members will be aware, we have already opened the C2 centre. We've already opened the M Plus Pavilion. The Free Space building will open this month with the Christian Rizzo show. We will then be opening M Plus as we've heard, end of next year, early 2021.
So the size, the exhibition centre itself is around forty-seven thousand square metres in terms of GFA. The hotel element and the office was about eighty-one thousand, and the retail, dining and entertainment proportion just under seven thousand square metres. So it's about one hundred and thirty-five.
successfully through that period.
One party or another, it has to be apportioned appropriately.
We want to develop this as a single project with all three elements.
We would be talking in terms of millions when we open the Palace Museum. Further millions, we're talking about large numbers of people coming to the district. We want these facilities to be up to standard.
The retail dining and entertainment elements obviously have to complement both the hotel and the exhibition facilities, but also have regard to that which will exist elsewhere within the district.
所以基本參數、the requirements，gross exhibition space of around 18,000 square metres. Obviously, this will be subject to the design, and if they can get in more, then that would be welcomed. We need
One of the key outcomes from the point of view of the district is that the exhibition must consistently attract premium international events as well as local be available for local events. We want this to be recognised as a leading world-class multi-purpose facility.
The other thing which I think is very important is that we must ensure that the A.C.E. integrates well with the other arts and culture facilities within the district and is a complementary and beneficial addition to the offering. Because bearing in mind
for the hotel we're providing a minimum gross floor area of 21,000 square metres and we're talking about the standard of what we call high tariff B quality. Rental offices, of course, similar to all the rest of the hotel office residential development in the district, we're looking at grade A quality.
A 10,000-seat concert hall with suitable acoustics to allow for indoor performances. We also expect it to be column-free and to have the appropriate services that need to be provided for anyone going to an indoor concert.
We're asking them to develop an exhibition centre as an art and culture facility, and this is in accordance with our approved development plan. And of course, we want to ensure that it achieves the same high world-class standards that we are achieving with all of the other projects that we're undertaking in the district.
We will be adopting an open and competitive tendering approach to select a private sector partner, and the expression of interest stage is the first stage in that process. This follows almost a year of consultation that we have undertaken to ensure that we understand exactly what the market interest.
and we also understand what the potential in terms of the opportunities that will arise in this project. For example, it's important to understand that we we have carried out some work. There was a demand study for new convention and exhibition.
所以時間表，The Expression of Interest Exercise，as I said，we announced this morning，and the start will be the 12th of June。It will carry through till the 12th of August，and within that time frame，we would expect people to submit their expression of interest with basic information as to who。
proper formal tendering, which we expect to take forward towards the end of this year, and we'll be talking about about four months for the submission of the tender period. We're hoping that we'll be able to award the tender for this in Q3 of two thousand and twenty, and as I said, completion of the work.
and to do so we need to harness the expertise, the experience, the capability of private sector developers and facility operators. I emphasise the facility operators because this is not a simple project of putting up a building and walking away. We expect to have a long-term relationship.
從， The
and in doing so.
finally, we're looking at providing a flexible venue.
available first and foremost for arts and culture uses.
新 exhibitions， but also for the expansion of existing exhibitions and events.
for the the convenience and the ease of access, so we see it as very much an integral approach.
它 is intended, as I said earlier, to meet what is already known to be unmet demand in Hong Kong for both.
That can provide a range of services available for demand from both performances, but also for events, for exhibitions and
now the figures that I'm showing here, 132,500 square metres of additional space. This was one of the results of the demand study that was conducted recently.
The priority, as with all of our facilities in the district, must be arts and culture-led. That doesn't mean to say that there can't be other types of users, but the priority in our view is that it should be.
as I say, particularly related to arts and culture, but and the creative industries as well. We see the hotel as an integral part of this, and it's very important because, as members know, if you have an event space, often people like to stay overnight.
With the successful tenderer, this is a project that we envisage seeing a development period of about five years, followed by an operation period of about thirty years. That is a long-term relationship, and we need to be certain that the successful tenderer can not only complete but operate.
Districts point of view, we obviously want to see a financial return to the West Kalim Cultural District Authority, and to achieve that, we need to look at an optimal risk allocation between the tenderer and the authority. It does not play in this sort of project to expect all of the risk to be borne by one.
The fact that we are already seeing large numbers of visitors, you saw the figures that were just produced on M+ for for events that we've been doing there. I can say that already since the opening of the Sea2Centre, we've had 56,000 people through that in just a few months. When we open the M+,
Finally, the approach is, as I said, a build-operate-transfer arrangement, which we were calling a public-private partnership. We're calling it this because we have established within the authority a public-private partnership committee to oversee all of our HR development.
including the ACE, from planning procurement right through to development and operation. The procurement guidelines will also available on our website, so that they are transparent for those people who are interested in this. Let me stress two final points. The
Expression of interest documentation will be available from the 12th. It is not free. We are charging five thousand dollars to cover our costs. But also, we think that it's important that people are genuinely interested in taking this thing forward and not just simply picking up another bit of paper. The second point I want to emphasise is that.
In terms of the requirements that I've set out, they will be part and parcel of the contractual terms, and we will also be monitoring and working with the final selected tenderer because we see this as a partnership arrangement. We're not simply saying take the site, walk away and give it.
唔該。
佢用途咧就係一個非工業用途嘅。
公眾休憩用地啦，四咧就係停車場、落貨依啲位置啦。
五咧就係關於轉讓嘅問題啦。咁六咧就係政。
法區管理局。咁以下落嚟咧，我誒會簡介一下誒草擬嗰時咧，我哋一啲嘅特別嘅考慮點啊，同埋一啲嘅主要嘅內容嘅。
最終其實會係交畀係邊一個去真係去決定咧？我哋咧就會係委託翻係西九文化區管理局咧嘅董事局去決定，究竟邊一啲文化藝術用途咧係適宜喺西九文化區裏邊係係使用嘅。
嘅咁而土地啱啱都睇到啦，其實佢個發展期咧，亦都係非常之長嘅。咁故此，我哋都亦亦都係需要係就住依方面咧，係提供一個彈性，亦都希望能夠將使嗰嘅整體發展咧，能夠更加全面同埋融合嘅。
政要向政府就住發展誒個項目裏邊咧，係要向政府係支付一個前期款項呢個規定，同埋喺建造營運移交協議到期之後咧，係管理局係需要同政府攤分呢啲嘅項目所產生嘅收入嘅一啲嘅重要嘅條款嘅。
We don't think that that's an appropriate approach. We expect to be engaged, not least because if we have a ten zero event in the ACE site and we also have a ten zero event in the park next door, we would have to deal with coordination on crowd dispersal. We'd have to deal with coordination on transport.
etc.，所以partnership is very much the watchword for our approach on this. I will end here and pass on, and I will have to do this for you, I suspect. Thank you. No problem. Preparation of the land grant. Okay，多謝各位。咁或者我以下落嚟咧係講一講咧，就為住西九文化區嗰個地方咧，誒政府所擬備一個批。
批地文件嘅，其實呢個批地文件咧，我哋都係誒預備咗好長時間嘅。噉啊，亦都喺上個月誒廿八號咧，行政長官咧會同行政會議咧，亦都係已經同意咧，係批出呢一個土地咧，係畀西九管理局啊，係以漲徵息一千蚊嘅地價免誒免行政費咧，係五十年期咧批畀誒，將會批畀誒西九誒文。
咁其實西九文化區咧係一個非常之誒獨特嘅一個嘅發展項目嚟嘅。咁首先嚟講咧，喺文化區裏邊咧，我哋會包含咗好多唔同嘅文化藝術啦。咁大家都會知道文化藝術其實依個定義同埋範圍，佢個表現形態各各樣嚟講咧，都會隨住時間咧喺社會人士嚟講咧，會係有唔同嘅變。
法啦，所以嚟講咧，我哋喺一個批定文件裏邊咧，唔可以喺現階段嚟講咧，好單一地羅列曬有可能出現嘅一啲嘅文化藝術嘅嘅嘅表演形態或者個範圍嘅。故此，我哋個批定文件裏邊咧係會唔會就住一類咧係定定咗個咩叫做誒文化藝術，反而係畀一個更加廣闊嘅一個考慮誒。
咁而喺過往裏邊嘅諮詢期間咧，其實大家誒都會發現到好多持份者同埋社會大眾咧，都係普遍咧係支持西九咧依個發展項目咧，係需要一個係有機發展嘅模式。正正好似啱啱所講咧，配合翻文化藝術與時並進誒演變依一個嘅方向嘅。咁而文化藝術到最
咁跟住誒，另外有兩個特點咧，就大家都會知道啦。其實西九文化區咧，我哋咧係經過誒誒三階段諮詢之後咧，係採納咗誒冧誒Four-Sign Partner嗰個城市中地花園呢個設計概念嘅。咁令到所有嘅好多唔同嘅發展用途咧，喺個縱向或者橫向嚟講咧，都係高度融合嘅，亦都有。
好熱嘅。
係靈活去誒施加依啲嘅管制嘅。
協合作咧，以一個任何嘅形式咧，就去推展嘅。
二十五萬五千平方米嘅嘅文化藝術設施嘅嘅樓面面積嘅。
咁跟住落嚟咧，就講一講嗰個嘅誒繳付畀政府之嘅前期嘅款項。
咁至於係其他，譬如誒公眾休憩用地啦，我哋都係指定咗五年要提供十二公頃，十年要提供到十六公頃。
咁如果標書裏邊所定明所誒所提出嘅前期款項咧，係唔係不合理地低過預先釐定一個十足嘅市值嘅咧？係管理局係有權可以取消依啲嘅相關嘅招標嘅。
咁而喺誒，譬如喺嗰個誒政府機構啊、停車呢啲位置咧，因為佢我哋喺現階段嚟講咧，係要留翻一個彈性咧，係所以嚟講咧，就將呢啲嘅嘅規定咧，就擺咗喺備忘錄裏邊嘅。
咁而啱啱誒就住轉讓嚟講咧，依一度咧就係比較誒誒誒複雜好多㗎啦。咁首先一一樣咧就係話，我哋係唔容許管理局咧係將九將西嗰地段咧係作任何嘅轉讓，所以個業權咧係永遠係喺西九誒管理局嘅手上高嘅。
咁而我哋都反而咧係要容許管理局咧就住西九嘅地方喺唔同嘅發展嘅情況底下咧，係同一啲私人機構就合作去共同發展嘅。咁亦都容許咧就呢啲嘅誒誒私人合作機構咧就住呢個分租租契產生嘅權益咧，係進行一啲嘅按揭或者一啲抵押嘅誒用途嘅。
個叫綜合地庫依一個嘅嘅一個好龐大嘅建建築項目啦。咁故此嚟講咧，我哋都發現到依一個噉嘅模式嚟講咧，如果我哋係唔能唔將土地係一單用一個單一契約模式去誒附託畀誒管理局嚟講咧，其實佢個推展咧係會係有嗰個非常大嘅複雜性。
咁以下落嚟，我講講誒誒批地文件一啲嘅誒重要要點嘅。咁其實批地文件啱啱都講過啦，佢嗰個誒使用用途咧，我哋係定咗一個比較闊啲嘅誒範圍嘅，係為之係非工業，唔包括貨倉或者加油加油站呢啲用途。咁而喺有七樣誒比較重要嘅課題裏。
邊一啲嘅主要條款咧？我哋另外咧就會同誒管理過咧簽訂一份嘅備忘錄。咁而依份備忘錄咧會同批地文件係會同時簽訂同埋同時生效嘅。咁呢七項主要誒誒嘅類別咧係包括啲乜嘢咧？第一就係文化藝術設施嘅一啲嘅規定，第二係政府機構社區設施啦，三就係誒。
咁嗱，依度可以睇到咧，其實有啲就住一啲嘅發展咧，我哋會係有啲嘅條款咧擺咗喺批地文件，有啲係擺咗喺備忘錄裏邊嘅。譬如喺一個總樓面面積裏邊嚟講啦，批地文件會定明個總樓面面積係幾多啦，而亦都規定最大嘅酒店、辦公室、住宅發展總樓面面積咧，不可以多過。
個三十六萬六千誒六百二十平方米啦。咁而喺避難島裏邊咧，我哋咧就會定定咗文化藝術設施個樓誒樓面面積唔能夠細過三十七三十三萬幾啦。咁而亦都喺個時間上高嚟講，亦都規定咗喺十年內咧要提供唔能夠少過業。
咁而喺誒備忘裏邊咧，亦都會要定明咗咧董管理局嘅董事局要就住分租分租租契產生嘅權益等等呢啲各各方面嘅事宜咧嘅管制條文咧，係要作出一個嘅誒管制嘅。咁亦都會容許管理局係就住每一個個個別嘅個案咧。
咁喺嘅備忘錄入邊咧，亦都會規定咗，好似啱啱啊誒所提到啦，就住酒店、辦公室、住宅發展項目同埋A A C E依個項目咧，一定係需要透過建造營運移交依個形式咧去推展嘅。而其餘嗰啲文化藝術設施嚟講咧，就可以容許管理過得同任何嘅誒公司。
誒，邊位回應？
被磨多呢啲嘅重要內容。
咁以上嚟講咧，就係一啲嘅嘅批定文件同埋誒。
或者首先我答幾句誒，多謝主席誒，多謝抗抗議關心。嗱，首先咧啊，當然誒。
咁萬一收唔到意向書又點咧？即係萬一咧，我估計應該有嘅，但係萬一收唔到意向書又點處理咧？噉樣，陳主席。
需要啦，譬如佢個資金係係用嚟係做管理、營運、維修嘅嘅用途啦，同埋其他一啲嘅經常性資金嘅需要啦。
而令到佢舒緩赤字嘅一啲收入啦。咁其次就係誒，即係我見我注意到咧，就係嗰個嘅誒意向書咧，佢而家嚟緊就會收㗎啦。
到當時或者仲有啲嘅未償還嘅貸款或者債券融資咧，嗰個嘅嘅還款嘅問題啦，同埋一啲週轉資金同埋現金儲備等等依啲嘅嚟講咧，我哋都會係到時咧都會考慮翻依一啲嘅誒財務上嘅要求咧，去釐定翻依一個嘅貪分建議係合唔合理嘅。
係噉，首先嚟講咧，就係啱啱都提到啦，好似A C E個項目咧，一定係要用透過一個公開同埋一個嘅公平嘅一個招標嘅競具競爭性嘅招標程序去決定啦。咁而管理局咧，亦都係係就住所有項目，除咗A C E呢個項目之外咧，係需要係係將。
將一個嘅嘅前期嘅款項咧，係要求嘅發展商係提交依個誒嘅嘅銀碼。咁而依個銀碼咧係會將會係入去誒政府嘅庫房嘅。而管理局喺依啲嘅項目裏邊咧，係唔可以分再向誒依啲發展商要求或者收取任何其他嘅前期款。
跟住最後咧，就亦都喺備忘錄邊咧，亦都提到一個好重重要嘅項目啊。就就係當呢啲嘅建造營運或者移交合約期滿之後咧，佢將會亦都有會有龐大嘅收入嘅。咁呢個收入嘅安排係應該係點樣啊？咁呢度係會定明咗喺呢啲嘅合約期滿之後咧，所有嘅收入。
管理局咧係需要同政府係作作一個攤分嘅，而呢個攤分呢個建議咧就會係提交畀行政長官會同行政會議去批准嘅。咁考慮呢啲嘅攤分建議裏邊咧，其實政府到時咧就會考慮翻當時管理局嗰個需要嘅資金營運管理嗰個。
好多謝啊，應女士。咁而家就係議員發問嘅時間，都係四分鐘啦。咁首先請啊，康俊宇議員。啊，多謝主席。噉啊，當然係即係繼續關注呢一個西九嘅財赤問題，因為事實上二零一九、二零二零至二零二一、二零二二咧就三十一點四。
億嗰個嘅即係面對嗰個赤字，二零一八一九咧嗰個營運開支赤字二千七百萬咧，其實咧而家一路咧即係西九都係話期待呢隻金蛋啦，呢隻金蛋就係呢個A C E呢一個嘅即係組合噉樣啦。咁但係我哋而家睇啲時間表咧，就二零二五年，即係即係誒，如果啊講緊去而家收。
意向書啊，亦都喺今年第三季做招標，噉啊，二零二五年咧理想地就應該可以生得出呢只金蛋嘅。但係我，我問題想問，會唔會係呢只金蛋未出現之前咧，佢哋已經已死死咗咧？因為而家個問題係在於第一，我哋掌握唔到佢啊，即係大概幾時可以即係收到第一筆可以。
誒土地咧係用咗做高鐵嘅工地，咁所以由於佢遲咗。
令你擔心，即係二零二五年咧就落成咁幾時預期收到第一筆收成咧？如果唔係咧，你不斷蝕咧，蝕到入肉都唔係好掂當。
嗰本咧係誒分攤一啲係嘅誒租務同埋其他嘅收入嘅。咁睇下阿柏志高先生有冇補充？Just to supplement, because I think Permanent Secretary has very accurately described the situation. We have a number of different income streams.
我哋唔知道下一年度嘅立法會會唔會繼續有呢個小組啦嚇。咁如果假設繼續有呢個小組咧，誒，我哋其實都係承諾咗係每年嘅四月咧，係要向小組咧係匯報一次西九嘅最新嘅誒財政情況嘅。咁所以咧即係誒唔使擔。
心即係我哋會一路誒會誒，就算有冇呢個小組，如果冇咗，我哋就會喺翻誒民政事務局嗰個誒誒事務小組嚇個委員會會向大家報告嘅。咁第二樣嘢，關於呢只誒A C嘅發展，呢個所謂金蛋啦嚇。咁其實咧，大家誒喺上。
上一次四月底，誒西九嘅主席同大家討論嗰個誒誒匯報嘅財政情況嘅時候咧，喺個附件一咧已經係羅列咗一係列嘅因素嘅。其中一樣嘢咧，點解西九個財赤喺過去嗰幾年係誒都係上升咧？主要係因為誒誒有部分嘅。
交畀西九做一個發展，咁所以大部分所謂可以有一個誒經常性嘅收入，包括呢個A C E啦，包括誒零售啊、餐飲、消閒啲設施咧，都係比以往嘅估算咧係遲咗幾年先至可以開始發展嘅。咁希望大家明白，因為而家。
啦，誒，無論係文化項目啊，西九園係一個建築期內，所以咧誒，暫時係未有收入，咁所以佢只有係支出。佢嘅唯一嘅收入咧，就係所謂嘅，就算票價都係戲曲中心嗰啲，咁亦都係杯水車薪啦。咁另外一啲咧就係誒一啲所謂誒誒募捐啦。咁但係大家亦都。
知道即係募捐，當你未有硬件嘅時候咧，誒，你都係比較難嘅。咁呢一方面咧，誒，政府係西九管理局咧，亦都係好嚴格咁審視緊佢個財財政嘅情況。所以我好擔心啊，即係誒，李司長，因為嗰個赤字咧，即係近乎黑洞噉。咁而家我。
嗱咁誒，康議員咧，多謝你嘅關心。其實我哋都一樣咁關心嘅。咁但係大家明白咧，其實有時話西九誒所謂超支呢個字咧，其實對西九文化區咧就唔係好坦白講唔係好公允嘅，因為喺誒二零零八年當已經二百一十六億批畀佢嘅時候咧。
其實嗰陣時嗰個誒，即係我重新講嗰次嗰陣時嗰個概念圖啊等等都未出嚟嘅。咁所謂如果講係咪有超支，我諗係應該按佢一個獨立嘅項目，譬如話M加戲曲中心到佢賣賣show嘅時候，係咪同佢當日嘅招標價或者預算嗰個建築成本嘅相比咧？
我諗噉樣去講，佢有冇超支係會比較公允，用翻誒誒，而唔係用嗰二百一十六億去計。因為二百一十六億畀佢嘅時候咧，所謂呢個endowment呢個一開始畀佢嘅款項咧，其實嗰陣時都未有一個發展投資走出嚟。咁發展投資咧係去到二零一三年初先至決。
It's about income.
秘書長。
那係，係
哦，即係話佢係唔需要抵收，係抵消開支，只不過係個收入。
酒店、office和residential，所以喺
係咪抵需收即係開誒嗰個誒收入係唔需要誒再分攤落嗰啲咩文化開誒藝術開支嘅係咪？
啊，江議員，你今日問曬啲問題，我諗財委會嗰陣時唔需要再問啦，係咪？哇！主席，你真係睇得起我，到時可能有更加即係深度嘅問題咧，多謝主席。
The tenderers will sorry, not the profit sharing, the income sharing proposal that the tenderers will bid against. So please don't misunderstand. It's not about profit.
咧，如果係出現誒盈利嘅話咧，即係要等到三十年之後個合約到期啦，政府先至可以分攤嗰啲有關嘅收入，係咪？
上邊嘅上蓋咧係冇得起嘅，咁所以我諗咧，如果想佢快啲收支平衡咧，就快啲批個綜合地庫，因為越遲開始起咧，嗰個建築成本咧係會攀升得好快咯嚇。多謝。
O.K.跟住係誒姚思榮議員。誒，郭主席，誒，我想誒問就係有關個批地文件同埋備忘錄個重點入面咧，有關誒建造營運同埋移交合約期滿，誒嗰個期滿係咪即係五十年啊？
定二零一四年咧，亦都有一啲改動嘅嚇。經過誒誒城規會嘅同意，咁所以希望大家明白咧。如果用嗰二百一十六億做一個緊箍咒去睇佢咧，其實就唔係太公允嘅。咁當然啦，喺未來嘅歲月咧，誒西九亦都明白咧，喺個董事局亦都好關心咧，係西九嘅財政上。
係咪能夠係誒誒係可以誒誒比較穩健去發展嘅？咁呢個我亦都知道咧，西九係最近咧亦都揾咗一個誒財務嘅顧問去幫佢睇睇誒往後係應該點樣去管理嘅。因為大家我亦都講翻咧，就算昔日喺嗰個加強財務安排底下咧。
咧都係話誒，佢係需要去到二零二三、二四年咧，都開始要諗融資嘅安排嘅。咁所以從來咧誒，我哋亦都冇向誒委員係隱瞞，就係去到二零誒二零年代中嘅時候咧，其實西九係要考慮一啲融資嘅安排。咁而融資嘅安排係。
包括係咪是否去市場借貸啦，亦都其中一啲財務安排，亦都包括同私人嘅發展商合作發展佢呢個誒展覽啊、酒店啊、辦公室啊、住宅嘅項目，誒，以期令到佢能夠喺嗰個合約期內咧係可以同呢個發展商嘅誒火。
We have income, obviously from our investment of the 21.6 billion, and we've been living off that for the last few years. But that money, of course, will now be spent very quickly as we start to pay off the projects that are now underway. We have income from ticketing and entry to.
And that will grow. You saw the figures earlier, fifty-six thousand. Each one of those people, of course, paid for a ticket to get in and see. And as we open more facilities, that resource will increase. We have income that we also derive from the retail, dining and entertainment. Again, Cherry has touched on that. We will also
也有收入從贊助和捐款，和在事實上我們有了一些收入從這些來源已經在過去幾年，不是巨大的金額，但坦白説，直到我們開始打開和運營設施，我並不期望有許多，但坦白説，長期解決我們的問題，與發展H。
HOR the hotel office and residential and us being able to share in the income that is derived from that more commercial operation and that's something which the ACE is the first step. We will follow that very rapidly. I hope by the end of this year with at least another four projects also taking forward.
主席，誒，如果可以的話，我好想補充多一點嘅。其實我都知道誒，好多議員咧好關心文化藝術嘅發展。如果大家係關心西九文化藝術嘅發展同埋西九嘅收支平衡咧，我希望誒財委會係能夠盡快批綜合地庫嘅發展，因為冇咗呢個綜合地庫咧。
咧，我哋。
個兩層嘅關係。首先係政府同西九文化區嘅關係嚇，政府批地批畀西九文化區就五十年。
分成有關嘅收入啊嘛，係咪？誒主席，誒主席，誒多謝姚議員關心。誒我相信呢個情況係唔會發生嘅。誒有幾個原因，點解我會對呢方面係都比較上有信心去答你啦？第一，西九管理局嘅成員係政府委任嘅。
係，不是不是幾時係咁？譬如好似而家誒A C E個項目啦，如果佢誒最終批出嚟咧係五年營運期加三十誒五年建造期加三十年營運期咧，其實個B O T咧就係三十五年嘅。咁三十五年之後咧，咁A C E嘅收入咧就會係需要管理局咧就要。
考慮咧，當時佢嘅財政狀況咧，考慮需唔需要就住A.C.E嘅收入咧，係同政府作作行一個單分嘅。係啦，噉係，但係我想問咧，就係嗱，如果係當三十年開始A.C.E誒已經批咗出去啦，即係開始有收入啦，係咪？咁收入入面咧，咁抵除誒，即係抵抵消咗開支之後。
Mr. Chairman, we don't look at profit. We look at total income, and we take a share of the total income. It's not about profit. We have no regard. The profit is for the commercial side. We look at the total turnover and we expect a share of that. And under the BOT, one of the issues that we'll be looking at in the context of the tender.
咁而係西九文化區攞咗呢個五十年期嘅誒土地契約嘅權之後咧，佢咧就會通過一個同私人機構合作，去畀呢個發展呢個發展同埋營運權呢個私人機構。咁呢一個咧，佢哋我知道西九咧係今朝已經開咗記者招待會啦。
咁五年嘅建築期，然後不少於三十年嘅合作期。咁喺呢三十年裏邊咧，咁西九咧就其實咧係會視乎而家啲人表達嗰個誒發展意向。噉佢收到人哋嘅資料之後咧，佢自己做咗分析。咁於是我相信西九文化區咧就會擬定一個標書，係對西九文。
化區係最有利啦。咁個標書咧，根據而家誒初步頭先啊，柏志高先生都解釋啦，佢就會係希望釐定係話佢哋嘅收入嘅一個部分要交畀西九。咁當然個發展商佢建築期建築嘅成本係佢出㗎嘛，噉佢都會相信佢由嗰個嘅收入裏邊。
係誒逐步係收翻佢息入投放嘅資本嘅。咁喺呢個噉嘅合約期期間咧，就主要個分攤嘅收入就係西九同呢個誒發展嘅合作商。呢個發展合作商咧，相信佢除咗發展商之外咧，都有一啲其他係誒係譬如經營一。
一個誒誒展覽嘅誒酒店啊等等有經驗嘅人嘅，咁當西九收咗呢個收入咧，西九咧就會將呢個收入係支撐佢其他西九嘅發展，包括文化藝術其他個項目嘅發展嘅。咁譬如嗱，因為而家佢係話不少於三十年合作期，我哋。
唔知幾多，因為都要等佢分析咗個意向書先至可以知道。假設嚇，假設係三十年，三十年即係話三十五年之後咧，佢嘅合約就完啦。咁之後咁西九個發展商咪要將成樣嘢交翻畀西九啦，啲硬件起完，咁西九就要到時咧係要同政府。
去傾啊！咁西九會比較建議政府，咁政府就視乎嗰個睇個整盤嘅嘅嘢啦。嗱，呢一樣嘢咧係喺誒第十五段文件嘅第十五段附件二嘅第十五段有講過。我哋會睇埋誒管理局到時需要嘅資金安排啊、誒佢嘅維修費用啊等等，而我。
嗱，如果你寫個三十年，你出標書咧？
誒個標價一定會低，即係政府收翻嚟嗰個嘅收益。
噉你剩落嚟，所以你想話五年建造期之後，嗰個啊營運期就可不少於三十年。
誒，我就想問嗱，我又唔相信政府咧喺誒由批地畀西九管理局誒文化區五十年之後會收翻嚟做第二個用途。
有呢一個噉嘅承諾喺嗰度咧，我相信佢翻嚟嗰個標書咧，嗰個吸引力會大啲啊。對政府嚟講，誒呢一個例子其實喺機管局係出現過嘅啊，即係我覺得你哋民政都西九都可以考慮。
我哋咧就會決定政府其實分攤幾多呢個收入嘅，因為大家會知道咧。頭先我講過喺嗰個加強財務安排入邊咧，其實咧係管理局都開始要諗融資嘅安排嘅。咁到時我哋相信咧，誒西嘅管理局咧都可能會有啲融，由於個融資安排而需要肩負嘅一。
一啲誒誒財政嘅負擔㗎，咁而家誒更加詳細嘅資料我哋未有啦。但係到時我哋相信咧，喺佢同發展商嘅合約期滿之後咧，我哋會有更加確切嘅資料。到時特區政府再會同西九決定係應該點樣分攤嗰個收入啦。O.K.咁誒，如果係呢三十五年內。
內咧西九出現一個龐大嘅盈餘嚇喺呢個情況之下咧，即係咪政府都唔會過問呢個龐大盈餘點樣去使？包括佢誒分紅畀誒員工啦，或者分分紅畀管理層啦。因為你政府係唔過問，去到三十五年之後，你先要決定點樣去誒分。
嚇咁第二樣嘢咧，就其實喺當初嘅加強財務安排有第三期嘅一啲發展項目咧，其實係要當西九係嘅財政上係比較上係穩健嘅時候咧，佢再發展嘅。咁所以其實佢一紮文化藝術嘅項目咧，佢要繼續去發展嘅。咁而第三咧，經營文化。
藝術項目咧，其實係全世界，就算一啲比較成熟嘅項目咧，都唔會收支平衡嘅。即係嗰個票務啊，或者租務等等嘅收入咧，通常咧都係誒cover咗大概係三四成嘅咋。咁其他嗰啲咧，佢都要衝過去誒籌款啊、捐獻啊、其他嘅部分去抵足嘅，即係佢去去補。
翻嘅噉，所以我相信係話誒西九去到誒好多誒係唔會發生㗎。同埋，我相信到時候社會同埋管理局入邊咧，都會有呢個訴求咧，係佢哋如果真係財政非常之穩健咧，係會期望佢哋將呢啲係發展香港嘅文化藝術，而唔係職員去分紅。
噉我相信喺管理局入邊嘅成員咧，亦都會係有呢個誒社會大眾嘅關注會知道嘅。咁而喺個管理局入邊咧，我哋亦都有三位嘅誒誒局長咧作為成員嘅嚇。即即我理解就A.C.E撥埋畀西九管理局之後，底。
燒埋所有嘅基本開支，即係政府都測算過咧，即係都係唔夠誒一日常嘅開支嘅，係咪？即係你測算過㗎啦，已經係。誒，主席。誒誒，多謝主席，多謝謠言。我唔可以話我測算過啦，而係話誒，你可以想像得到一個，如果你係個發展商，你要
自己出曬一個建築成本去起一嚿咁龐大嘅嚇，我哋講緊嘅係誒喺個GFA個發展嘅地就係十三萬五千幾個平方米嘅嚇，噉我相信嗰個建築成本係一啲都唔平嘅，咁嗰個誒發展商佢亦都會建。
建議，我相信會建議一個誒分攤收入，係令到佢喺營運期間係會有一個合理嘅回報嘅嚇。咁嗰橛咧究竟有幾多畀西九咧？我唔知道啦嚇。咁而西九喺嗰個時間咧，西九亦都要將呢筆錢咧，佢可能係要處理翻佢融資安排入邊嘅一啲負擔。
啱，噉佢仲要發展佢剩翻落嚟嘅項目，噉佢仲有一啲員工嘅收入嘅支出，同埋佢亦都營運一啲文化藝術嘅設施嘅，咁所以咧，因為大家要知道咧，文化藝術都一個好好好，都可以好昂貴嘅嚇，咁所以咧，我諗其實誒。
個經驗咧，呢個延長咗個年期咧，政府即係喺你翻嚟個收益係大好多嘅，啊，即係即係請你哋考慮嘅。
我聽打嘅嗰個年期咧越長係越有利嘅啊！咁又似乎根據經管局嘅經驗咧，呢樣嘢係可以考慮嘅。我唔知你哋會唔會咁諗咧？
總總睇埋咧，誒，我哋相信喺嗰個合作期間內咧，誒，西九唔會話真係非常之鬆裕嘅。咁當然，誒，我哋覺得呢啲都係一個暫時嚟講會係一個概念上嘅誒退效嘅。咁所以西九佢係而家揾咗個。
誒專業嘅誒財務顧問去睇誒佢未來嘅財務安排嘅，咁同一時間咧，我哋民政事務局咧亦都會我哋自己會委任一個獨立嘅喺市場，我哋揾有一個獨立嘅誒財務嘅專家，亦都到時會協助我哋去睇西九個盤數嘅嚇。
咁因為我相信誒，即係你哋亦都要問責於政府。咁政府亦都有責任咧，係確保西九。我哋一開始講咧，就係我哋需要西九係有足夠嘅資金，但係唔係過分嘅資金，唔係過分多嘅資金去營運呢個文化藝術嘅項目嘅嚇。譯志明議員。
唔該，主席誒，秘書長都解釋得誒非常清楚。咁誒就誒P P P個concept，我當然係支持啦。誒，但係咧我就有個問題嘅，就係嗰個點解係三十年咁短咧？咁咁頭先，因為我相信當日政府批地畀西九係應該五十年啦，一般嘅做法。噉你扣除咗啲時間。
啊，咁所以咧，誒會唔會考慮就係話誒將佢擴展翻去五十年？不過有嗰個剩餘嘅年期咧，就subject to誒，如果第西九管理局能夠同政府爭取到個延期係去到再延長嘅話咧，你會畀翻足五十年畀佢嗱。如果你
咁另外一個咧就係誒頭先你講三十年後誒完咗啦，佢個營運期噉。然之後政府再研究咧點去處理咧，我係有啲奇怪，因為點解咧？我唔相信西九管理局咧到時會有一班專場去識得管酒店啊，識得去管呢啲管我哋嘅噉。所以其實咧理論上咧就將你而家嗰個。
李署長，主席啊，多謝啊譯議員嘅提問，即係佢肯定將呢樣，即係花咗不少心思去睇呢樣嘢啦。噉我哋頭先我講過係一個兩層嘅關係，我哋批地畀西九管理局係五十年嘅，咁而家誒西九管理局邀誒今朝講喺個記者招待會都話一個不少。
少於三十年嘅咁誒，至於誒實際嘅年期係幾多，我相信西九管理局睇到個發展意向書之後會再做分析嘅。咁當然咧誒誒土地係香港最珍貴嘅資源，咁誒行政長官會同行政會議咧誒，佢係最後咧有一個誒決定權嘅噉。
噉我哋喺個誒備忘錄入邊規定咧，就係BOT嘅合約年期咧，最後要得到政府同意嘅。咁如果喺個BOT合約嘅年期嘅上限，西九管理局係需要有調整嘅時候，係要求調整咧。咁西九管理局到時咪畀理據我哋，我哋就要去行政會議去誒申。
正批准啦。咁另外，你講到話係誒西九管理局有冇呢個噉嘅誒誒誒所謂有冇噉嘅專長去管理酒店咧？其實正正你講到熱問題嘅核心，點解我哋係要規定西九管理局一定要用B.O.T嘅形式咧？其實呢個係。
係誒背後咧，係有兩個嘅考慮因素嘅。第一，我哋希望西九管理局咧，縱使佢有一個中向橫向係一個單一嘅發展嘅概念嚇，但係我哋亦都唔希望西九管理局咧係有一個所謂mission drift，即係話誒誒將個比重擺咗喺發展。
展地產而唔係做文化藝術，咁所以就正如柏志高先生當才講，呢個BOT嘅形式啊，係希望佢可以係利用到私人發展商同埋私人界別，無論係管理啊、建築等等嘅專長，亦都令到世界館嚟講唔需要孭一啲與發
誒，多謝主席。
唔知阿發小先生有冇補充啊？
烤，the longer the better。 of course， and that goes without saying， absolutely。跟住係馬逢國議員。
that it's a balancing act between when we get it back ourselves and therefore can benefit from the maximum income.
確地講出咗誒誒啟德體育園嗰個誒經驗，我哋亦都大大家睇到啟德講誒啟德啟誒啟德。
投標西九呢個項目咧，都會係除咗發展商之外咧，發展商一定都會揾埋相關需要嘅嘅專家嘅。咁所以到到最後，究竟係？
不少於三十年入邊嘅係幾多年咧？同埋係要求西九要求個分攤嘅收入係如何咧？噉我諗而家係言之尚早嘅，要等西九喺今年年尾收到嗰啲意向書嘅時候，做完分析，噉我相信會有即係更加好嘅齊備嘅資料咯。
今日我可以問得曬，咁所以我都好希望咧，即係喺會後咧，同即係無論西九管理局也好，或者民政事務局也好咧，有一個比較詳細少少嘅嘅即係討論同埋，即係希望可以解答啦。咁喺呢度咧，我只係想問幾個問題啫，就頭先阿Mr. Pascal講嘅就係話。
分嘅分成咧，只係計誒收入，就唔係計成本。噉我都好想瞭解清楚咧，呢個收入係點樣去定義？即係到底係誒營運收入啊，定係所有收入啊，定係誒咩嘅收入咧？係扣唔扣除一般營運嘅，譬如話？
展呢啲項目需要咩嘅風險？個風險轉嫁咗嚇，噉我覺得呢個係第一個考慮。第二個考慮咧就喺營運嘅期間，佢亦都可以係失攞個收入，但係等個營運嘅呢啲係交畀一啲私人嘅合作商去做，佢就專心去做文化藝術啦。咁當然都個合約期。
滿咗之後咧，係西九管理嘅到時咧係唔排除佢可以再招標人嚟幫佢去管理篤得㗎。因為我諗而家大家都知道，亦都私人機構係不少一啲起完一啲酒店，係請一啲世界知名嘅酒店管理集團去做嘅。咁當然呢個係幾十年後嘅事啦。咁但係我想講咧。
就係話政府喺決定呢個噉嘅比較複雜嘅一個批地嘅安排同埋BOT背後咧，其實主要係想西九誒呢啲發展嘅項目係支援西九財政上嘅需要，但係我哋唔希望佢係誒令到佢對。
於文化藝術嘅專注係受到過分嘅影響嘅嚇。啊，主席，誒，我係絕對同意嘅，即係P P P同埋B U T，我只不過係提出一樣嘢咧，因為你起呢一嚿嘢咧，裏邊其中一個都幾大嘅部分咧，係一個展誒展覽場同埋可以做呢個誒演唱會。咁咧，今時今日如果你有
個噉嘅演唱會都好受歡迎嘅場地，咁但係咧，你知道嚟緊好多競爭㗎嘛啊！咁呢個誒，第日嗰個誒誒啟德體育城嗰度又可以做啦，五萬人添係咪？咁誒誒機場嗰度而家又搞緊啲新嘅嘢啦，係咪？又收翻嗰個誒H O L Expo，又會有啲新嘢去搞啦，即係跟住。
你嗰個沙中線嗰個站上邊就有一啲新嘅場地啦，咁即係而因為呢一啲嘅項目咧係唔能夠係比較難去評估嘅收入㗎。你唔同話我開間酒店，又或者我誒做寫字樓，咁呢個比較容易去估計。咁所以變咗咧，如果你但係你如果誒認到呢啲場地好惡，因為如果我作為投資者去。
做呢個B.O.T. part啦，我梗係要保障自己啦。噉我可能將佢嘅收費搞到好貴，入邊咧而家啲人就投訴啦，戲曲中心啊唔好租啦，太貴啊噉。即係嗱，噉我純粹我係完全支持你哋嘅理念嘅，只不過咧，我係提出點解係三十年啫，唔應該點解唔擺長啲咧，擺多個provision落去，因為根據我睇到。
啊，秘書長誒，主席，我想再澄清一點咧，就係誒西九誒，其實而家係一個好聰明嘅做法。佢唔會一開始自己寫標書，佢要求個市場話畀佢聽誒一啲興趣、一啲意向，然後收咗呢啲資料，佢再做分析，然後佢先至去決定個標書點寫嘅。
咁所以變咗令到佢係一個比較上得到較多市場嘅準確嘅資訊底下去釐定個標書。噉我哋誒民政事務局同埋其他嘅政府部門作為西九管理局入邊嘅成員咧，都覺得呢個比較審慎嘅做法㗎。咁第二啊，譯議員咧亦都好正。
你先問。
誒。
係冇啊！
sorry，誒呢個誒藝術。
時候嘅一筆費用，咁文經都講咧，如果太細咧、太少咧，咁政府可能會收回個標書嘅。
Between ourselves and and government, is to be determined by us carrying out a
會，它 help us at all? It doesn't help us. The income and we'll come to the definition that we derive from the share.
Mr. Chairman, I'll deal with the upfront payment issue first, and then I'll ask William to deal with the the definition of income. The upfront payment, as defined.
銀行借貸啦，誒，同埋即係如果話太少嘅時候就會收回咧。咁咩叫太少咧？咁呢呢個係一個我希望問清楚嘅問題。或者我先問住呢幾個問題先啦，代主席。
體育園咧，佢其實牽頭係一個發展商，但係呢個發展商咧，亦都咧，其實唔係自己做曬嘅。佢係一個集團式，入邊係包括一啲營運、餐飲啊、營運運動方面係國際知名嘅專家組成呢個集團嘅。噉我有理由相信咧，係到時可能。
I think I think Cherry's made the point very well. We want to listen. We have heard during the previous consultation exercise that a longer period would be better, so we're aware of that. And I don't disagree with your analysis. I think it's a very valid analysis. But we we also have regard to the fact.
rather than sharing it, but also giving a reasonable time frame through which a tender successful tenderer can successfully recoup their investment and make their profit. It's that balance, and so that this is what exactly as Cherries explained, something we'll be looking at when we get to the tender stage. I think at end of the day, no matter
誒即係睇咗份文件咧，同埋聽咗頭先啊白兆高先生嘅介紹同埋誒上邊嘅介紹啦。誒我自己因為曾經做咗十年嘅西九董事啦，咁所以非常關心呢個計劃。噉我哋兜兜轉轉，由最初咧係單一發展模式，到到收尾咧就分開咗。誒政府承擔二百一十六億。
到到而家咧就分久必合咧，又將重新整合，咁但係就改咗少少嘅，就三十年嘅誒使用權同埋五年嘅建設時間噉樣。噉我我對呢一個噉嘅財務安排咧，我冇咩特殊嘅意見嘅。咁但係咧對詳細嘅內容咧，其實我有仲有好多問題，我唔相信咧。
燈油火蠟啦、誒節舊啦等等嘅嘅嘅即係開支咧，咁定係定係點樣嘅咧？咁呢個一個啦。咁誒，另外一個問題咧就係即係講有一筆誒，無論邊個中標咧，就會有一筆最起碼嘅upfront payment，即係開始嘅。
誒藝術展覽中心係冇嘅，冇呢個upfront payment係H.O.R.先有嘅，即係hotel office仲誒residence。我我我明白，即係我我就想問就話呢一個噉嘅upfront嘅payment咧，到底嗰個誒係幾多咧？政府打算係幾多咧？咩先叫太少咧？咁？
咁而誒，我又想問啦，呢一筆噉嘅收入啦，嚇，即係誒payment啦，咁誒要唔要同政府去攤分啦？又或者呢一筆噉嘅費用咧，係咪足唔足夠咧？係可以畀誒西九管理局咧去營運佢嚟緊，仲要需要嘅額外開支，而唔需要去銀行向。
We will employ three different independent assessments to come up with what we call a full market value. That will then be discussed with the government, consider what the appropriate payment is, and all of that upfront payment goes to government. None of it comes to the authority. So it's not a question of.
which is bid by the tenderer is what we have to survive on until we get the final return in thirty odd years, whatever. So as far as the upfront payment, that applies only to the hotel office and residential components, not to ACE, and that's one of the special conditions that.
啊！
咁咧。
佢話咧。
咁咧就。
如果你 want to,
擺咗個山。
種咗攞種子。
嗰個訪問，佢嗰個。
十幾年啦，食到眼瓊瓊。
我咧都想有幾個問題問一問。
睇到有一個種榴蓮啊，貓山榴蓮嘅，喺馬來西亞。
我過過去兩日咧，就我都睇咗一啲紀錄片。
borrowing if you want that can be used to help fund some of our projects, but we can't mortgage our properties. That's very very important to understand.
And just to make it very clear, of course, in the context of the contractual arrangements, we will have full transparency on that income stream. So we will see the books to ensure that we know exactly what that income is.
have been applied in this case. In this case, we're not allowed to accept an upfront payment either, even though that would be quite an attractive thing for us to do. So we would ask the tenderer to bid against the income share that they would offer to us as part of the deal. So perhaps we.
Just one follow-up question. It implies that the WKCD still have to arrange a mortgage with the with the contract. No. To secure extra funding. No, because well, I think the the question is, will we need to raise funds commercially?
to support the project, yes, not necessarily a mortgage because we don't mortgage our property, we can't dispose of our property, but we could raise bonds, we could raise loans, we can raise commercial paper. There are options, and this is what Cherry was describing that we are looking at with our financial advisers. So that is a form of
即係。
記者咧就。
即係滿盤滿盤。
咁咧，而家賺到佢話。
由十蚊賣到七十蚊。
M加啦，仲有其他嘅。
日日咧係誒一日好過一日嘅。
故宮博物館啊，等等啦，大家都好期待嘅。
噉啊！但係都要等到二零二五年先至落成。
咁誒嗱，今日我哋討論嗰個A.C.嘅項目。
噉啊，戲曲中心啦，而家我哋講到。
咁咧，講講緊係呢個馬拉子喎。
誒起出嚟啦！咁咧，其實各界咧香即係香港市民都好期待嘅。
咁亦都睇到西九一座一座嗰啲建築物咧，一路路。
享受佢而家種出嚟嘅成果啦，好香！啊，每一個咧～
噉我作為西九呢個誒成員啦，呢個籌備委員會嘅董事啦，啊，同埋第一屆嘅董事啦，噉我睇到嗰個進展咧，確實係。
嗯。
李先生。
而家譬如日後嗱。
build咗operate，你對於個operator。
理據嘅，噉我我其實想問一問咧。
咁但係點都好，噉你哋一定有你哋嘅原因去提出呢個BOT嘅。
唔係好滿意嚇，譬如響使誒依個使用個效率嗰方面啦，收費嗰方面啦。
噉啊，社會上亦亦都有一啲迴響嘅，即係即係對於佢整個營運，噉你哋啊政府有啲乜嘢？
咁至於頭先你講到話啊，如果個營運者不滿嘅時候咧，我會稍後請阿柏志高先生講講嘅。但我相信咧，作為誒管理局嘅成員之一咧，
方法可以處理得到嘅咧啊？點樣？如果真係做得唔好嘅，點樣令到佢可以做得好啲啊，或者更好嘅咧？
噉係咪有啲遲咧？遲都唔緊要，最緊要係好。嗱，今次就係用一個BOT嘅形式咧，就去啊興建嘅。咁呢個同啟德嗰個有啲唔同。
府要睇同西九坐低傾，係有一部分係咪要誒點樣做咧？剩翻係咪同政府分攤翻我收入？因為政府可以我哋將呢啲收入去支持西九以外嘅文化藝術發展，或者做其他嘅公營用途嘅。
一個政府，政府亦都會要求佢嘅標書入邊咧，同西格同嗰個發展合作商，佢同個合作商嘅合約裏邊一定要定明一啲所謂嘅performance indicator，一啲表現嘅準則等等嘅。或者我睇阿柏先生詳細講。
啊噉啊，彭粉員，個個啊主席嚇啊個煙琴啊，所謂收入嘅定義啊，其實我哋我哋最相對用最簡單嘅方法，所有收翻嚟嘅錢嚇係冇得扣減嘅嚇，即係所有任租金收翻嚟就係咁多咁多，其實成本係幾多咧嚇？依我哋唔係計算在內，咁呢個我哋因為要係簡簡單而明，但係當然咧。
但係將來嘅定義咧，就會好複雜。但係嗰個一係比較，我哋而家嘅C.D.R.幫你啊寫緊嗰啲條款咧，其實都幾好詳細。但係咧，一定要係啊冇基本上都係講得好清楚嚇，係收入嚟嘅錢基本上都係都係算作收入啊，就唔扣除嘅營經經營成本啊呢方面嘅嘢嘅啊，你噉。
多謝主席。誒或者我首先誒comment我一點咧，就係誒你嘅記憶好好，你嘅記憶非常之好。即係誒喺嗰個B.O.T.營運嘅期間咧，誒其實誒誒嗰個營運者咧係會同西九分攤個收入，但係當呢個B.O.T.期完咗之後咧，成嚿呢啲commercial facility
咧係畀翻西九嘅時候咧，誒大家要記住呢個臨海面對海嘅一個A級甲級嘅寫字樓嘅土地嚟嘅，咁所以我哋相信嗰陣時西九嘅總收入咧，如果成舊嘢咧係會好多下嘅，咁所以點解政府就係話呢個BOT完咗之後咧，政府
Mr. Chairman, just very similar, we will have performance indicators (KPI). We also have remedy in the sense that we can instruct the removal or replacement of an operator. We can also require, because we have full transparency on income, we will also require remedies to be put forward.
係。
呃。
咁呢一個誒？
馬富國議員第第二輪。
誒要營運。
我我諗，大家都期待。
即係呢一個PowerPoint裏邊講嘅有幾樣嘢咧，就係。
唔少於二十五萬五千平方。
點樣去去界定嘅咧？即係邊一啲屬於？
咁誒，另外咧就係即係關於嗰個。
文化藝術設施咧，即係就要喺十年之內咧，就係要。
誒多謝主席，我其實頭先有個問題都未答喎，就係即係文件都講，即係如果嗰個誒。
啊！隨住戲曲中心之後，啊M加啊博物館等等咧，就可以提供一個好嘅場地畀我哋香港市民去使用嚇。
即係嗰個誒投標嘅時候個分成，如果唔係好合理咧，或者低嘅話咧，即係就會考慮即係取消嗰個招標嘅。噉我話即係有冇一個大概嘅點樣先為之唔低咧？咁呢呢個係第一個問題啦。
議員其實問到個問題核心咧，就係話。
加強財務安排係一個好聰明嘅做法嘅，即係佢會睇到昔日城規會話嗰個發展嘅上限，整咗一個總樓面面積出嚟。
誒點解要畀嗰個前期嘅款項個upfront payment？其實佢問到嘅問題咧，係觸及到個upfront payment成個概念喺邊度嚇？
係文化藝術設施邊啲唔屬於咧？譬如話嗰個誒展覽中心又屬唔屬於咧？即係呢呢個點解係定呢個咧？誒又點解係即係誒誒？
意向書之後，佢會定嘅標書。西九定嘅標書可能規定話，你最低限度每年要畀我幾多錢，而啊，亦都要按比例點樣分攤畀幾多畀我。我唔知道啦，西九到時決定。
一個總嘅樓面面積，裏邊咧有一個係最高上限嘅一啲商業嘅用途啊、酒店啊、辦公室、住宅發展，然後文化設施係一個最起碼嘅意思，即係話任何嘅。
點解唔係？點解要十年之內要做到呢個咧？咁同嗰個誒，譬如話建設嗰個呢一呢一呢一係列嘅誒設施嘅嗰嗰五年嘅建築期有咩關係嘅咧？係包含咗裏邊咧，定係唔包含裏邊嘅咧？
係，阿秘書長。誒誒，多謝主席，多謝馬員。誒馬員嘅問題咧係問得好獨到嘅嚇。咁咧就誒，其實誒，如果你睇翻個powerpoint咧，我覺得誒識嘅前人做呢個噉嘅誒。
但係發展商睇完佢嘅建築成本，睇完佢要撥畀西九嘅一個攤分嘅收入，於是佢諗下啦，我作為一個發展商、在商言商，我仲可以攞幾多錢出嚟畀政府呢個upfront payment？即係以換句話講咧，佢同西九享分享嘅誒收益。
In the first instance, if the performance is not up to standard, so all of these are all going to be embedded within the contractual terms. The the other question you asked, what's the difference between this and the KITAK project? Of course, the difference is that we expect the private sector to pay for this. We won't pay any money. KITAK, of course, government has paid.
正如我正話講咧，西九一棟一棟嘅藝術建築物咧就起好噉，其實收費嗰度大家都關注嘅。其實最緊要嘅咧就係裏邊有一啲好質素嘅展覽同埋表演咧，即係可以畀到我哋香港市民嘅。噉我我哋都期待啊！
突咗出嚟嘅人就一定係做文化、文化藝術嘅，即係你睇到嗰個巧妙處，所以我覺得佢好聰明地咧係確保西九文化區咧呢一啲嘅商業元素咧，只係愛嚟一個支撐西九而西九嘅主調咧係做文化藝術嘅。我覺得噉樣睇啦。第二啊，馬逢剛。
同埋何謂之低咧？嗱，大家要諗下點解我哋就住A C E唔收H O L要收咧？因為A C我哋其實睇到兩樣嘢，第一，香港其實總體嚟講咧係缺乏一啲展覽場地嘅，咁所以一個展覽場地嘅發展咧係對香港整體有裨益，唔止係對西九有好處。另外一
個展覽場地咧，亦都正如頭先阿譚志明議員亦都好提及咯。展覽場地其實亦都可以愛嚟做一啲文化藝術啊嘅表演嘅。咁所以我哋睇到呢一個嘅exhibition facility嘅發展咧，其實係對整體香港有裨益，所以我哋咧就覺得唔收upfront payment。但係點解HOL要收咧？嗱，大家。
可唔可以跟進啊，主席？我畀多咗兩分鐘你。嗱，其實咧，我我跟住想問嘅問題咧，就係。
誒誒，我講少少，然後誒呢個其他嗰啲咩誒租嗰啲，我就交畀阿柏志高先生。誒，我淨係想講講咧，係誒。
誒唔好意思，個長比較長，因為但係如果唔理解背後嘅概念咧，就好難即係明白到背後好一個好複雜嘅設置啦嚇。
點啊？譬如話會唔會有一個長租嘅安誒嘅優惠啊？又或者有咩嘅措施係確保佢係有一個文化藝術嘅性質咧？對，主席。
唔係一個完全係主觀嘅憶測，我哋到時有三個專家同私人發展商一樣望住西九標書嘅條件，而大家去定呢個價錢出嚟㗎嚇。
地，頭先我講過係香港最寶貴嘅資源啊嘛，噉我哋就要求西九文化局咧係要委託三個獨立嘅專家睇翻佢定出嚟嘅標書條件之後咧，如果佢用翻一個市場嘅
而家睇翻香港政府以往一個叫象徵式地價咧，通常只會畀一啲非型誒叫做咩誒誒一啲係非牟利嘅嘅誒性質嘅，但係H.O.R.本身就係一個商業元素嚟嘅。咁但係政府而家又畀佢象徵式一千蚊畀。
起曬呢塊地，咁點樣將呢兩種嘅嘢去結合咧？就係用呢個好巧妙嘅方法，因為政府唔係話自己攞錢起咗曬商業嘅大廈，然後就話啊呢棟嘢就愛嚟做生金蛋嘅嘅生金蛋嘅我，然後就啲錢畀誒西九，唔係咁做，因為政府知道。
其實政府比起商界係冇咁叻㗎，做呢啲嘢噉，所以正如阿柏志高先生嘅介紹咧，我哋利用商界嘅專長去發展呢啲嘢。咁由於我哋要商界自己出呢個發展成本，咁如果你又要去出個地價，又要佢出個發展成本，然後佢嗰個收入又要同西九攤分。
係會好難，好難吸引到私人嘅興趣嘅。咁所以我哋就係話嗱，發展商你係要出錢喺啲舊嘢嘅喺嗰個合約B.O.T.嘅合約期間，你係要同西九攤翻啲嘅收入嘅喺噉嘅條件下，喺西九定嘅條件，因為你知道西九到時十二月收到個發展。
佢攞出嚟要發展呢個項目，同佢到時upfront payment就整體等於佢喺平常裏邊要畀個地價出嚟。咁所以何為低高咧？啊，馬議員，我哋就到時點解頭先阿柏志高先生講啦，我哋再會揾要求，誒，為咗保障市民嘅利益，因為
去睇呢三個獨立嘅專家話畀我哋聽，佢如果係佢的話咧，佢就會畀個乜嘢amount payment出嚟啦。噉我哋就用呢三個嘅專家計出嚟嘅數去評估一個真正嘅市場落標書嘅數，睇下係咪合理啦。咁所以呢個呢個是否合理咧？唔。
即係，既然呢四萬平方米嘅展覽中心，即係而家嘅定義，基本上係一個文化藝術設施啦，所以你唔收佢嗰個upfront payment。好啦，咁既然係文化藝術設施，咁但係呢樣講咧，即係文化藝術嗰個定義咧，是否文化藝術嘅嘅性質咧，就由西九管理局去定嘅。咁如果定咗之後咧，我。
我我就都想問呢個文化藝術嘅定義，而家有冇一個好即係一個好標準嘅説法咧？咁咁而既然係咁定咗咧，咁將來嗰個用呢個展覽中心嘅場地嘅時候咧，誒應該理論上就係文化藝術有一個優先使用嘅安排嘅。噉我亦都想瞭解下咧，即係嗰個安排會係點？
喺呢個誒exhibition centre入邊咧，正如我講咧，佢係可以支撐文化藝術嘅發展，同埋，但係我哋亦都知道香港係缺乏呢個展覽嘅場地嘅。咁另外咧，我哋會將誒文化嗰個定義係交畀西九管理局，因為喺呢一度咧，我想提出兩點咧，就係話。
第一喺嗰個法例底下咧，係政府雖然特首有個委任誒誒委員嘅權，但係個法例亦都要求特首係要委任一啲係包括係喺文化藝術有相當嘅經驗嘅人咧入去呢個局。
嘅噉，亦都喺個法例入邊咧，西九係要做一啲誒公眾嘅誒誒諮詢活動，所以佢有一個常設嘅諮詢委員會嘅嚇。噉我哋亦都最後一點，我想講咧，就係大家亦都睇到真係文化藝術嘅展現方式，正如頭先應女士講咧，係隨住。
誒時代係會轉變，譬如以往我哋認為係純粹係I.T.一啲嘢，而家喺舞台上咧都好多I.T.嘅展現，咁呢啲係咪文化藝術咧？而家我相信咧係都冇人會否認佢哋係嘅。咁至於真真正正嘅exhibition centre嘅營運等等，我交畀柏志高先生去補充。簡短啲好嘛，阿柏。
徵求大家個意見。
即係我唔知點樣去理解呢樣嘢咯。
to those developments and we will.
我係想徵詢委員嘅意見。
咁下一個事項咧，就係其他事項。
誒講咩？聽唔到，唔好意思。可唔可以？我諗發circulation啦，係咪可以？
咁依個就係有關延展聯合小組委員會工作期嘅建議。
咁如果委員係同意延展工作期嘅建議咧，秘書處咧就會就建議。
延展聯合小組委員會嘅工作，即係我哋依個小組委員會嘅工作。如果係大家同意嘅咧，我就要秘書處誒。
石橋好啦，今日環節咧，我仲想澄清一樣嘢，即係頭先阿Mr. Pascal講嘅樣嘢咧，我都好似有少少矛盾。一方面咧，我哋講緊呢個呢個特別一個文化藝術嘅設施，但係另外一方面咧，佢就強調呢個係純商業嘅運作。噉我覺得呢樣嘢本身係有矛盾。
好噉啊！多謝政府官員同埋西九嘅代表咧，今日嚟介紹有關A.C.E.啊嘅近期發展。
而備嘅文件咧，啊，公發展及民政兩個事務委員會考慮獲得兩個事務委員會嘅支持之後咧，就會向內務委員會提交報告，咁以徵求佢哋嘅批准，噉就我想。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Let me just make two comments. The first one is, no, I don't anticipate us putting any concessionary rates in. This is a commercial activity, and if they if they choose to do their concessionary rates, that would be a matter for them to consider, bearing in mind, of course, the impact on their income and turnover.
In so far as the definition of arts and culture is concerned, the approach that we take is that we have a committee that considers applications already. For example, for booking of our facilities, and as we develop greater use of more facilities, the definition becomes more refined.
Generally speaking, it's what you would expect. In other words, if it has artistic merit at a professional level, then it's artistic. If it has artistic merit at a less professional or less than professional level, you have to start questioning whether that would be appropriate. If it has amateur standard, then
Again, you would take a view on that. So the priority, even now, is always professional first, less than professional than amateur, and then everybody else. So the definitions are already there, but it's not set in stone. As Cherry quite rightly said, art is developing all the time, and we have to respond.
no, not at all. the the ACE project is a commercial enterprise. it's why we're tapping in to the commercial sector to operate it. if we as an authority decide to make use of the space for whatever reason, we'll have to pay them because it comes from their income. so it is a commercial enterprise, not
噉啊，秘書處咧亦都係啊，草擬咗一份文件嘅。噉就我哋呢個聯合小組委員會係唔係需要延展工作啊嘅期限咧？響二零一九至二零二零年度會會期啊，亦繼續運作嘅建議咧？
O.K.
有冇其他事項，委員長提出？
如果冇嘅咧，我宣佈今日嘅會議結束。
噉我就將有關嘅文件咧傳譯畀各委員。
做一份文件，我哋交內會，我哋要求佢哋誒繼續延展我哋依個委員會嘅工作。
係啦，咁問啊，我我哋係啦，因為我哋有兩，因為依個係一個聯合嘅委員會，有民政同埋依個發展委員會嘅，噉我哋都需要傳越嘅，或者我哋大家同意嘅咧。